A Guide to the Winthrop J.V. Osterhout papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA186
Rockefeller Archive Center
Winthrop J. V. Osterhout papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Osterhout, W. J. V. (Winthrop John Van Leuven)
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA186
1.32 Cubic Feet 3 boxes and 5 volumes.
Biographical/Historical note
Winthrop John Vanleuven Osterhout, physiologist, succeeded Jacques Loeb as head of the Division of General Physiology at The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research in 1925. His influence upon students, colleagues, and the biological audience in general was exerted toward quantitative data and mathematical analysis of biological processes. He was an editor of The Journal of General Physiology for 45 years, beginning with its founding in 1919.
Biographical note
1871 Born August 2, Brooklyn, New York
1893 A.B. Brown University
1894 A.M. Brown University
1893-1895 Instructor in Botany; Brown University
1894-1895 Wood's Hole, Massachusetts
1895-1896 University of Bonn (student with Eduard Strasburger)
1896-1901 Instructor in Botany; University of California
1899 Ph. D. University of California
1901-1908 Assistant Professor University of California
1908-1909 Associate Professor University of California
1909-1913 Assistant Professor Harvard University
1913-1925 Professor Harvard University
1920-1926 Member Board of Scientific Directors Rockefeller Institute
1925 Sc. D. (honorary) Harvard
1926 Ph. D. Brown University
1925-1939 Member, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
1939- Member Emeritus RIMR
1964 Died April 9 in New York, NY. Ashes buried in cemetery of St. James the Less, Philadelphia, Pa.
1910- Trustee Marine Biological Lab., Wood's Hole, Mass.
1919-1964 Co-Editor The Journal of General Physiology
Member of: A.A.A.S. Fellow, National Academy of Sciences of America, American Philosophical Society, Botanical Society of America, American Society of Naturalists, Academy of Arts and Sciences, NY Academy of Sciences, Botanical Society, Edinburgh, American Physiological Society, Society of Experimental Biology & Medicine, American Chemical Society, Century Club, Kungliga Fysiog. Sallskapet, Lund, Leopold-Carolin Deutsche Akademie der Naturforscher (Halle).
Scope and Contents note
Bibliography, photographs, illustrations, Collected reprints.
Arrangement note
Arranged by subject.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 OS7
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Related Materials
The Osterhout papers which consist of about 750 items are at the American Philosophical Society. An inventory of these papers are in box 1.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Box 1 received or inventoried: September, 1974. Box 2 and Box 3 added to collection May 1980 form the Office of Faculty Records.
Mathematics; Physiology; Biology -- Research; Medical research; Life sciences; Rockefeller University; Osterhout, W. J. V. (Winthrop John Van Leuven); Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
- Biographical material, photographs and bibliography (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes correspondence 1933-1940 with copies of correspondence 1924 on his appointment as Member of RIMR. Correspondence deals with retirement provisions and allowance for widow.
  Includes reprint from "The Development of Harvard University" 1869-1929, Chapter xxii: Botany; Biographical memoir. National Academy of Sciences, v. (1947)
- Film strips with explanatory notes (Box 1)
- Illustrations used in publications (Box 1)
- Notes (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Probably made by Marian Irwin Osterhout. Dealing with published works and first mentions of important developments contributed by W.J.V. Osterhout.
- Marian Irwin Osterhout (Box 1)
  Biographical / Historical
  (1888-1973)
  Bibliography, photograph; Half a Hundred Radcliffe Women.
  Several manuscripts which may not have been published.
- Correspondence, 1925-1935 (Box 1)
  28 letters between Marian Irwin (later Marian Irwin Osterhout) Simon Flexner and Edric Smith. The letters consist, primarily of administrative matters but includes letter of resignation 27 March 1933. The letters of Marian Osterhout are all handwritten.
- Collected Reprints, 5 volumes
- Collected Reprints, 1 volume
- Correspondence (Box 2 and 3)
  Consists primarily of administrative correspondence between Dr. Osterhout, Simon Flexner, and Business Manager. When Dr. Osterhout lost his sight the correspondence was carried on for him by his wife, Marian Irwin Osterhout.
  1 folder in Box 2 contains one photograph, reprint of "Physiological studies of single plant cells" from BIOLOGICAL REVIEWS 4 (1931); an outline of the history of The JOURNAL OF GENERAL PHYSIOLOGY; duplicate copies of WHO'S WHO information; 3 1939-1939 news clippings; copy of minute adopted by Board of Scientific Directors in 1939; bibliography 1925-1956; obituary from BROWN ALUMNI MONTHLY.
  Separated Materials note
  The Osterhout papers which consist of about 750 items are at the American Philosophical Society. An inventory of these papers is in Box 1.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Added to the collection May 1980, from the Office of Faculty records.
  - Letter concerning the naming of Tryparsamide, 1920 November (Box 2)
    (while a Member of the Board of Scientific Directors, December, 1919-1923)
  - Correspondence at the time of Jacques Loeb's death, 1924 (Box 2)
    February 11: arrangements regarding the editorship of JGP and later an invitation to become member of RIMR scientific staff.
  - Appointed to RIMR scientific staff, 1925 (Box 2)
  - January 1, 1926 resignation from Board of Scientific Directors, 1926-1927 (Box 2)
  - 1928-1929 (Box 2)
  - 1930-1933 (Box 2)
    Includes closing of Bermuda Station and February 28 marriage to Marian Irwin.
  - 1933-1940 (Box 3)
  - 1941-1950 (Box 3)
  - 1951-1973 (Box 3)
    Includes 1961 reconsideration of pension provisions and additional annuity for Mrs. O at Dr. O's death